Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association fonds
1895 - 1998
F-192
Q105635609
2.5 m of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the British Consul General and the Centre for Scottish Studies at Simon Fraser University (2004).
Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association
Organized in Toronto on June 27, 1876, the Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association is a fraternal association of Scottish people, their spouses, and their descendants in Canada. Its functions are to "preserve and promote Scottish heritage and culture in Canada" by maintaining Scottish historical, literary, and musical traditions, and to promote among its members a feeling of community and comradery. Additionally, the Sons of Scotland is a fraternal benefit association; membership dues entitle members to a certain amount of insurance coverage, which can be increased according to their needs.
The Sons of Scotland was incorporated by the Province of Ontario in 1880, and by the Dominion of Canada in 1937. It is governed by a central Executive Board in Toronto called the Grand Camp, which was established in 1878 and is headed by a Grand Chief and a Grand Chieftain. Grand Camp Executive officers are elected for three year terms. The Association is then divided into districts. There are currently four districts: Toronto District No. 7, Montreal District No. 14, Winnipeg District No. 15, and British Columbia District No. 16. The districts, in turn, consist of several camps, called subordinate camps. Each district and camp is governed by an Executive Board, which is headed by a chief and a chieftain. Executive officers of district and subordinate camps are elected on an annual basis.
In addition to regular meetings, the Association organizes and hosts social events, such as dances, dinners, picnics, and games.
published
Full
Published
The title is based on the name of the creating body.
Fonds consists of records relating to the organization and activities of the Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, particularly District No. 16 (British Columbia), and several of its subordinate camps, including Glamis Camp No. 210, Glengarry Camp No. 212, Lord Tweedsmuir Camp No. 209, Murray Camp No. 215, and Royal Scot Camp No. 172. Activities, events, and topics documented include the rules, rituals, and organization of the Association; the founding and development of some of the subordinate camps; meetings, activities, events, finances, and membership of District No. 16, its subordinate camps and, to a lesser degree, the Grand Camp; and correspondence and interaction among subordinate camps, as well as between subordinate camps, District No. 16, and the Grand Camp.
Records include minutes, minute books, and related papers; financial ledgers, cash books, financial statements, and financial reports; record books and note books; correspondence, reports, newsletters, and directories; constitutions and bylaws; lists; and programmes and promotional material.
The material was arranged into series by the Archivist according to the Association's organizational structure, with subordinate camps arranged alphabetically.
Cultural groups
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association and individual camps in three accessions from May 1, 2003-December 22, 2003.
All accessions have been processed as of December 2004. Further accruals are expected.
Access to some files containing personal information may be restricted. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File list is available.
- Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association records, 1945 - 1991; F-192-1; 5 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association constitutions and ritual procedures in booklet form. Constitutions and rituals apply to all Sons of Scotland camps; constitutions are revised and printed every three years.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Records were arranged first according to type of material, and then chronologically.
  Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association
  The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association in one accession on December 22, 2003.
  Access to some files containing personal information may be restricted. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Constitutions, 1945-1991, vol. 1, 1945 - 1963; F-192-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    Textual records
    Open
  - Constitutions, 1945-1991, vol. 2, 1963 - 1976; F-192-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
  - Constitutions, 1945-1991, vol. 3, 1976 - 1979; F-192-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
  - Constitutions, 1945-1991, vol. 4, 1979 - 1991; F-192-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
  - Booklet: Ritual of the Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, 1953 - 1972; F-192-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
- District No. 16 records, 1946 - 1991; F-192-2; 23 cm of textual records; Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association. District No. 16
  District No. 16 is the district for British Columbia, and has included camps in Burnaby, Vancouver, New Westminster, Chilliwack, Victoria, Vernon, and Prince George.
  Series consists of Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, District No. 16 minute books and camp directories.
  The arrangement into sub-series was provided by the archivist, according to type of material.
  Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association. District No. 16
  - Directories, 1946 - 1991; F-192-2-1; 7 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of directories listing information about District No. 16 and all of the camps in the District. Directories include contact information for district, camp and also Grand Camp officers; meeting places and times; dates that camps were instituted; and a list of camp events. Includes directories for 1946, 1948, 1950 to 1962, and 1964-1991.
    Files are arranged chronologically.
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 1, 1946 - 1948; F-192-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 2, 1950 - 1955; F-192-2-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 3, 1956 - 1959; F-192-2-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 4, 1960 - 1969; F-192-2-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 5, 1970 - 1979; F-192-2-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 6, 1980 - 1986; F-192-2-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
    - District No. 16 camp directories, 1946-1991, vol. 7, 1987 - 1991; F-192-2-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 192-1)
  - Minute books, 1957 - 1987; F-192-2-2; 16 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of District No. 16 minutes books, September 1957 through January 1988. Minute books include roll calls of delegates.
    - Minute book, 26 September 1957 - 30 December 1965; F-192-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-2)
    - Minute book, 27 January 1966 - 24 June 1971; F-192-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-2)
    - Minute book, 26 August 1971 - 30 November 1978; F-192-2-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-2)
    - Minute book, December 1978 to January 1988, 28 December 1978 - 16 December 1987; F-192-2-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-3)
- Glamis Camp, No. 210 minute books, 1937 - 1998; F-192-3; 39 cm of textual records; Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association. Glamis Camp, No. 210
  The Glamis Camp was established in the Kitsilano area of Vancouver on June 2, 1937. Thirty-seven members were initiated into the Camp at this first meeting. John Brown was chosen as Worthy Chief, and William Fraser as Chieftain. Annual dues for honorary members were three dollars; annual dues for active members were dependent upon the type of insurance they had. The Camp first met at Killarney Hall, at 2nd Avenue and Bayswater Street, but due to increased membership, began meeting in the larger Elks Hall at 901 Dunsmuir Street in April 1938. After January 1943, the Camp met in various downtown and Kitsilano locations. The Camp is still active, meeting monthly at the Scottish Cultural Centre at 8886 Hudson Street in South Vancouver.
  Series consists of records relating to meetings and activities of the Glamis Camp. Records include minute books, with related correspondence and other papers, dating from the Camp's establishment in June 1937 until 1998. Minute books include lists of new members and rolls of camp officers. Correspondence is mainly with other camps.
  The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by the Glamis Camp in one accession on May 1, 2003.
  - Minute book, 2 June 1937 - 7 March 1940; F-192-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-3)
  - Minute book, 4 April 1940 - 14 December 1943; F-192-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-3)
  - Minute book, 21 January 1944 - 11 February 1948; F-192-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-3)
  - Minute book, 20 February 1948 - 21 December 1951; F-192-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-4)
  - Minute book, January 1952 - 15 December 1955; F-192-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-4)
  - Minute book, 19 January 1956 - 17 December 1959; F-192-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 192-4)
  - Minute book, January 1960 to January 1964, 21 January 1960 - 7 February 1964; F-192-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 192-4)
  - Minute book, vol. 1, 20 February 1964 - 18 December 1969; F-192-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 192-5)
  - Minute book (enclosed correspondence), vol. 2, 20 February 1964 - 18 December 1969; F-192-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 192-5)
  - Minute book, 15 January 1970 - 20 November 1975; F-192-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 192-5)
  - Minute book, 15 January 1976 - 18 March 1982; F-192-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 192-5)
  - Minute book, 12 April 1982 - 11 December 1987; F-192-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 192-5)
  - Minute book, 21 January 1988 - 17 December 1992; F-192-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 192-6)
  - Minute book, 21 January 1993 - 8 January 1998; F-192-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 192-6)
- Glengarry Camp, No. 212 records, 1937 - 1989; F-192-4; 94 cm of textual records; Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association. Glengarry Camp, No. 212
  The inaugural meeting of the Glengarry Camp took place on December 10, 1937, and the Camp was officially instituted on December 13, 1937. Out of eighty-three applicants, sixty-seven new members were initiated. Worthy Chief was Mathew Grindley, and John Maclean was the Chieftain. The Camp met monthly at the I.O.O.F. Hall on Hastings Street at Kamloops Street. As of 1944, the initiation fee for active and honorary members was two dollars, and the quarterly fee for active members was one dollar and five cents. In May 1975, the Camp began holding joint meetings with the Montrose Camp. Executive positions were shared between the two camps. The camps continued to hold joint meetings until the Montrose Camp was disbanded on May 31, 1981, and approximately sixty Montrose members were integrated into the Glengarry Camp. As of 2004, the Camp continues to meet monthly, at the I.O.O.F. Hall at 7728 Edmonds St. in Burnaby.
  Series consists of records relating to the Glengarry Camp. Activities, events and topics documented include meetings and other activities of the Camp, its Executive Committee, Entertainment Committee, and Ladies Auxiliary; joint meetings with Montrose Camp, and activities and events of Montrose Camp during that period; the financial management of the Camp; and its relations with other District No. 16 camps. Records include minutes and minute books; financial statements, balance sheets, and financial reports; record books and note books; bylaws; correspondence, reports, and newletters; and lists.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist.
  - Committee and general meeting minutes and related records, 1937 - 1989; F-192-4-1; 70 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to meetings and activities of the Glengarry Camp and its Entertainment and Executive Committees, including joint meetings held with Montrose Camp. Includes minutes and related papers and notations, as well as lists of members, officers, and visitors. Records include minutes and minute books; record books and note books; bylaws; correspondence; and financial statements and reports.
    - General meeting minutes and related records, 1937 - 1989; F-192-4-1-1; 48 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of records relating to Glengarry Camp general meetings and activities. Includes minutes and related papers; notations pertaining to Camp members and events; and books recording the names of visitors and members attending meetings. Minute books date back to the inaugural meeting, and include rolls of officers and new member lists. Includes minutes of joint meetings of the Glengarry and Montrose camps held between May 8, 1975 and the Montrose Camp's dissolution in May 1981. Related papers include 1944 Camp bylaws; correspondence with District No. 16 and Grand Camp secretaries; financial statements and reports; and District Committee minutes (1954, 1981). Records include minutes and minute books; record books and note books; bylaws; correspondence; financial statements and reports; and programmes.
      The arrangement was provided by the archivist, first according to type of record, and then chronologically.
      - Minutes, December 10, 1937 to February 13, 1942 (summary, with original 1944 bylaws), 1944 - 1970; F-192-4-1-1-1 (Archival box - standard 192-6)
      - Minute book (#3), 12 February 1943 - 9 August 1946; F-192-4-1-1-2 (Archival box - standard 192-6)
      - Minute book (#4), 13 September 1946 - 9 February 1951; F-192-4-1-1-3 (Archival box - standard 192-6)
      - Minute book (#5), 9 March 1951 - 10 December 1954; F-192-4-1-1-4 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#5) (enclosures), vol. 2, 9 March 1951 - 10 December 1954; F-192-4-1-1-5 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#6), 14 January 1955 - 9 October 1959; F-192-4-1-1-6 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#7), 13 November 1959 - 12 June 1964; F-192-4-1-1-7 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#8), 10 July 1964 - 13 December 1968; F-192-4-1-1-8 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#9), 10 January 1969 - 8 December 1972; F-192-4-1-1-9 (Archival box - standard 192-7)
      - Minute book (#10), vol. 1, 12 January 1973 - 14 June 1976; F-192-4-1-1-10 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book (#10) (enclosures), vol. 2, 12 January 1973 - 14 June 1976; F-192-4-1-1-11 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book (#11), 11 June 1976 - 8 December 1978; F-192-4-1-1-12 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book [Glengarry and Montrose camps] (#12), vol. 1, 12 January 1979 - November 1981; F-192-4-1-1-13 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book [Glengarry and Montrose camps] (#12) (enclosures), vol. 2, 12 January 1979 - November 1981; F-192-4-1-1-14 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book (#13), December 1981 - 13 June 1988; F-192-4-1-1-15 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - Minute book (#13) (enclosures), vol. 2, December 1981 - 13 June 1988; F-192-4-1-1-16 (Archival box - standard 192-8)
      - [Original notations for minutes], 19 February 1979 - 12 December 1980; F-192-4-1-1-17 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - [Original notations for minutes], 9 January 1981 - 6 January 1982; F-192-4-1-1-18 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - Miscellaneous notes regarding Camp members and events, 1963 - 1971; F-192-4-1-1-19 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
        Pending review
      - Visitor's book, 10 December 1937 - 8 December 1944; F-192-4-1-1-20 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - Visitor's book, vol. 1, January 1945 - 5 April 1954; F-192-4-1-1-21 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - Visitor's book (enclosures), vol. 2, January 1945 - 5 April 1954; F-192-4-1-1-22 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - Visitor's book, 11 June 1954 - 14 November 1969; F-192-4-1-1-23 (Archival box - standard 192-9)
      - Visitor's book, December 1969 - 10 February 1989; F-192-4-1-1-24 (Archival box - standard 192-10)
    - Entertainment Committee minutes, 1947 - 1973; F-192-4-1-2; 11 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of records relating to meetings and activities of the Glengarry Camp Entertainment Committee. Records include minute books and related papers dating from January 1947 to November 1973. Minute books include rolls of officers. Related papers include 1939 Glengarry Camp bylaws and programmes for the Camp's Annual Burns Supper (1947-1961).
      - Entertainment Committee minute book, 22 January 1947 - 9 November 1958; F-192-4-1-2-1 (Archival box - standard 192-10)
      - Entertainment Committee minute book, January 1959 to January 5, 1973, 17 December 1958 - 5 January 1973; F-192-4-1-2-2 (Archival box - standard 192-10)
      - Entertainment Committee minute book, January 1959 to January 5, 1973 (enclosures), vol. 2, 17 December 1958 - 5 January 1973; F-192-4-1-2-3 (Archival box - standard 192-10)
      - Entertainment Committee minute book, 19 January 1973 - November 1973; F-192-4-1-2-4 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
    - Executive Committee minutes, 1943 - 1986; F-192-4-1-3; 11 cm of textual records
      Sub-sub-series consists of records relating to meetings and activities of the Glengarry Camp Executive Committee. Includes minutes of Executive Committee meetings (1958-1986), and notes taken at meetings, circa 1943 to 1949, regarding member information, Executive recommendations and motions, and other topics discussed at meetings. Records include minutes, minute books, and a note book.
      - Executive Committee meeting notes, recommendations, and motions, vol. 1, 1943 - 1949; F-192-4-1-3-1 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
      - Executive Committee meeting notes, recommendations, and motions, vol. 2, 1943 - 1949; F-192-4-1-3-2 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
      - Executive Committee minutes, January 1958 - October 1967; F-192-4-1-3-3 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
      - [Executive Committee] minute book, 3 November 1967 - 6 December 1974; F-192-4-1-3-4; Also includes material from 1947. (Archival box - standard 192-11)
      - Minute book - Executive Committee, vol. 1, 24 January 1975 - 19 November 1986; F-192-4-1-3-5 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
      - Minute book - Executive Committee (enclosures), vol. 2, 24 January 1975 - 19 November 1986; F-192-4-1-3-6 (Archival box - standard 192-11)
  - Financial records, 1941 - 1970; F-192-4-2; 9 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of financial records of the Glengarry Camp. Records include cash books, including a cash book for the Glengarry Social Club and a cash book relating to the Canadian Scottish Women's Corps; a Treasurer's book; membership dues accounts; and other financial statements.
    - Cash book, Canadian Scottish Women's Corps, 1941, 1941 - 1957; F-192-4-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Cash book #2, 1945 - 1970; F-192-4-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - The Bairns of Glengarry' Treasurer book, 1945 - 1963; F-192-4-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Cash book, The Thistles of Glengarry (Glengarry Social Club), 1949 - 1969; F-192-4-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Cash book, 1951 - 1956; F-192-4-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Membership dues and financial statements, 1951 - 1957; F-192-4-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
  - Ladies Auxiliary records, 1945 - 1970; F-192-4-3; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the membership and activities of the Ladies Auxiliary of the Glengarry Camp. Records include minute books documenting Auxiliary meetings (1945-1967), and a membership dues book (1959-1970).
    - Ladies Auxiliary Club minute book, vol. 1, 24 January 1945 - June 1957; F-192-4-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Ladies Auxiliary Club minute book (enclosures), vol. 2, 24 January 1945 - June 1957; F-192-4-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-12)
    - Ladies Auxiliary Club minute book, 4 September 1957 - 1 May 1963; F-192-4-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Ladies Auxiliary Club minute book, 5 June 1963 - 1 February 1967; F-192-4-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Ladies Auxiliary Club minutes [original notations], 2 December 1964 - 6 September 1967; F-192-4-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Ladies Auxiliary dues book, 1959 - 1970; F-192-4-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
  - Newsletters, correspondence, reports and other records, 1943 - 1981; F-192-4-4; 8 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of newsletters, correspondence, reports and other records documenting the Glengarry Camp's and, to a lesser degree, the Montrose Camp's activities, histories and traditions. Activities, events and topics documented include general Camp activities and special events; Glengarry Camp membership (1943-1946) and the names of past Chiefs for both camps; relations with other camps; and instructions for Marshall Openings. Includes a history of the Glengarry Camp for the period 1937 to 1957; Recording Secretary reports of Glengarry Camp activities, 1943 to 1968; a "Five Year History" of joint meetings with Montrose Camp, 1975 to 1980; Glengarry Camp newsletters (1968-1970); and joint Glengarry and Montrose Camp newsletters (circa 1980-1981). Also included are District No. 16 Committee by-laws (1971) and some newsletters of United Scottish Societies Auditorium Ltd. (1974-1981), a Vancouver company that the Glengarry Camp had shares in. Records include record books; reports, newletters, and correspondence; lists; by-laws; and balance sheets.
    The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Arrangement of material into files by the creator.
    - Report: A History of Glengarry Camp 212, Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, vol. 1, December 1937 to December 1942, 13 November 1970; F-192-4-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Report: A History of Glengarry Camp 212, Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, vol. 2, January 1943 to December 1947, 13 November 1970; F-192-4-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Report: A History of Glengarry Camp 212, Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, vol. 3, January 1948 to December 1952, 13 November 1970; F-192-4-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Report: A History of Glengarry Camp 212, Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, vol. 4, January 1953 to December 1957, 13 November 1970; F-192-4-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Report: A History of Glengarry Camp 212, Sons of Scotland Benevolent Association, 13 November 1970; F-192-4-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 192-13)
    - Report: Five year history, May 1975 to April 1980, of combined meetings of Glengarry #212 and Montrose #203 camps..., F-192-4-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 192-13)